<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | Least Astonished]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.leastastonished.com/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.leastastonished.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-27T08:51:59-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.leastastonished.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Warner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beware the Siren Song of Comments]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.leastastonished.com/blog/2014/08/27/beware-the-siren-song-of-comments/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-27T08:37:08-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.leastastonished.com/blog/2014/08/27/beware-the-siren-song-of-comments</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Developers love comments! Everyone who writes a comment thinks
that they&rsquo;re making a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_efficiency">pareto improvement</a> to the codebase, when
in fact it&rsquo;s quite the opposite. Comments are especially dangerous because there are many situations where it
<em>seems</em> like a comment will help, but beware the siren&rsquo;s call.</p>

<p>I hate reading articles that make abstract arguments, so enough bloviating, let&rsquo;s check out some examples.
Here are some concrete uses of comments that I&rsquo;ve seen a lot, and how they can be easily avoided.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Explaining some code</h3>

<p>You might want to write a comment to explain some code that isn&rsquo;t 100% intuitive. Let&rsquo;s
take a practical example from the <a href="http://genius.com">Genius</a> codebase:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Artist &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  before_save :set_canonical_name_changed

  private

  def set_canonical_name_changed
    self.canonical_name_changed = !!canonical_name.try(:name_changed?)
    nil # return nil because if canonical_name is unchanged, it'll return false, which halts save!
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>That comment helpfully explains that <code>ActiveRecord</code> will halt saving a model if one of the callbacks returns
<code>false</code>. So, we have to return <code>nil</code> instead. Whenever you&rsquo;re tempted to comment your code to explain what&rsquo;s going on,
the code isn&rsquo;t clear enough. Your goal should be to make the code readable on its own.
So how can we make this section clearer without a comment? Why not just write a helpful method which explains
what&rsquo;s going on, and can be easily reused?</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">ActiveRecord::Base.class_eval do
  def without_halting_save
    yield
    nil
  end
end

class Artist &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  before_save :set_canonical_name_changed

  private

  def set_canonical_name_changed
    without_halting_save do
      self.canonical_name_changed = !!canonical_name.try(:name_changed?)
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now we have the same amount of information, and a reusable method that explains its intent. Plus, now if
<code>ActiveRecord</code> changes its behavior, and returning nil suddenly starts halting save, we can change this method
and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_rising_tide_lifts_all_boats">lift all boats</a>.</p>

<h3>Explaining some performance hack</h3>

<p>Most of the time you can write readable code without worrying about performance, but sometimes performance
actually matters. When you have to write a performance hack, you might have an urge to write a comment explaining
why. The instinct to want to document your performance hack is the right one, but a comment is the wrong place.
Why? Because the hacky code might get modified, removed, or moved somewhere else, and the person who does that
has to remember to update the comment too. (Spoiler alert: they&rsquo;re not going to do it.) The comment will never
&ldquo;break&rdquo; and force someone to fix it if the behavior of the hack changes, it will just stick around to confuse
future programmers.</p>

<p>The right place to document hacks is a commit message. A commit message is easily accessible
to programmers wanting to edit the code, but it doesn&rsquo;t clog up the code and make
it harder to read. <code>git blame</code> allows you to see the commit message for any line that you&rsquo;re looking at.
Unlike comments, commit messages will never become out of date, because if the line that they&rsquo;re modifying gets deleted or modified, the commit message gets automatically &ldquo;removed&rdquo; from your view in <code>git blame</code>.</p>

<p>On any long-running project, your source control <em>is</em> your documentation. Disciplined development teams strive to
write code that, as much as possible, is self-documenting. When some code doesn&rsquo;t speak for itself, they leave
their notes in commit messages. If there is any additional discussion over some implementation detail or code
design in a pull request, it should be easy to find it right from source control.
<a href="http://www.leastastonished.com/blog/2014/03/06/git-getpull-quickly-find-the-pull-request-that-merged-your-commit-to-master/">git getpull</a>
allows you to find the GitHub pull request that merged the commit you&rsquo;re looking at, so you can quickly look
for any technical discussion about some implementation.</p>

<p>When I&rsquo;m writing a performance hack, I typically wrap it in a method explaining that it&rsquo;s a hack, and then write
a more detailed explanation in the commit message. For example, let&rsquo;s say I&rsquo;ve written some fast array compare
based on some specific knowledge of a data structure:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">
def some_complex_calculation_method(input_array)
  if compare_input_with_stored_values_performance_hack(self.stored_array, input_array)
    # ... something ...
  end
end

def compare_input_with_stored_values_performance_hack(stored_array, input_array)
  # here be dragons
end
</code></pre>

<p>All I need to do is to give the reader some clue that it&rsquo;s a performance hack, and then they can read more in
the commit message if they want.</p>

<h3>Reminder / TODO</h3>

<p>Writing <code>TODO</code> or <code>FIXME</code> somewhere in the codebase creates
a bit of a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bystander_effect">bystander effect</a>. It seems like the intent of the
TODO is that &ldquo;someone will surely see this code and proactively delete it&rdquo;, but in reality that will
never happen. Every time someone goes into that section of the code, they&rsquo;re in there for some other purpose
and they&rsquo;re going to ignore your TODO. This is especially true on bigger teams.</p>

<p>Example:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">require 'mylibrary/railtie' if defined?(Rails) # TODO: older rails support!
</code></pre>

<p>Realistically, when is that TODO ever going to get done? A better solution would be to use some project management
tool to prioritize different features or fixes. If you have to keep your <code>TODO</code>s in the code, use the
<a href="https://github.com/andyw8/do_by">doby</a> library, or roll your own expiring todos.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">TODO 'older rails support!', '2014-09-01'
require 'mylibrary/railtie' if defined?(Rails)
</code></pre>

<p>This method sets a specific due date for the <code>TODO</code>, and, unlike a regular comment, it actually gets executed
and blows up if you haven&rsquo;t removed it before the due date. (Buyer beware: you probably only want this behavior
in dev.)</p>

<h3>Old code you &ldquo;want to keep around&rdquo; in case you need it</h3>

<p>This is by far the worst commenting infraction! You might see a comment like:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby"># def reslug_all_tag_pages
#   Tag.find_each { |t| t.regenerate_slug! }
# end

def something_else_thats_actually_being_used
  ...
end
</code></pre>

<p>&ldquo;Keeping around old code you might want to use later&rdquo; is <em>exactly</em> what source control is for. If you want
to resurrect some old code, you can do so easily with git as long as you can remember some part of the
code. Let&rsquo;s say you want to resurrect this <code>reslug_all_tag_pages</code> method. Just use:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">$ git log -Sreslug_all_tag_pages
</code></pre>

<p>and that will find all commits that added or deleted a line including that string. Simple!</p>

<h3>Automatically generated comments</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s less common in the world of dynamic languages, but the most popular IDEs for compiled
languages tend to pepper the codebase with these useless automatically generated strings. They generate these
comments to remind programmers to document their APIs, but I&rsquo;ve frequently seen developers commit
the automatically generated documentation on a method or class without modification. Some examples:</p>

<pre><code class="java">public class MyList&lt;E&gt; extends ArrayList&lt;E&gt; {

  private int myVar;

  /**
   * @return the myVar
   */
  public int getMyVar() {
    return myVar;
  }

  /**
   * @param myVar the myVar to set
   */
  public void setMyVar(int myVar) {
    this.myVar = myVar;
  }

  /* (non-Javadoc)
   * @see java.util.ArrayList#addAll(java.util.Collection)
   */
  @Override
  public boolean addAll(Collection&lt;? extends E&gt; collection) {
    // something
  }

}
</code></pre>

<p>The generated comments do nothing but clutter up the code, making it more difficult for the reader to scroll
through the class and figure out what the code is doing.</p>

<h3>Is there ever a reason to write a comment?</h3>

<p>To be clear, I don&rsquo;t have a problem with all comments. If you&rsquo;re writing a public API for
a library that&rsquo;s getting exported to the world, or to a bunch of developers at your company, it may be
easiest to maintain the documentation for that API in code comments. In other words, if you&rsquo;re making a
conscious decision to document a library thoroughly, you might find that it&rsquo;s most convenient to keep that
documentation close to the code. In that case, you should have some kind of process for making sure that
the documentation remains up to date when you make breaking API changes. You should also be able to easily
generate structured documentation from those code comments.  (<a href="http://rdoc.sourceforge.net/">RDoc</a> for Ruby
is one simple example)</p>

<h3>Leave &lsquo;em out</h3>

<p>Comments decay. They aren&rsquo;t compiled, and they&rsquo;ll never get executed at runtime. If they become out of date or
incorrect, no test is going to fail and no user is going to complain.
Programmers work around them out of fear that &ldquo;somebody might need this comment or it might provide some value
in the future&rdquo;, pushing them along far after they&rsquo;re useful (if you can even argue that they were useful in
the first place).</p>

<p>Writing a comment to explain your code is the easy way out. It is more difficult to write expressive code than it is
to write a paragraph explaining it, but taking the time to write code that speaks for itself pays huge dividends in
the long run.</p>

<p>So now that I&rsquo;ve covered all of these examples, you don&rsquo;t have any excuse to write comments. Give these
methods a try, and I promise you&rsquo;ll have a cleaner codebase that&rsquo;s easier to maintain. Is there a good reason
to write a comment that I&rsquo;ve missed? Let me know in the comments!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
